<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8' standalone='yes'?>
<exception xmlns="http://bsi.bund.de/TR03151" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" id="ErrorDeregisterClientFailed" xsi:schemaLocation="http://bsi.bund.de/TR03151 ../../schema/exceptions.xsd">
  <name>ErrorDeregisterClientFailed</name>
  <description>This exception is thrown if the SE API function deregisterClient fails to disable the invocation of startTransaction, updateTransaction, and finishTransaction for the specified clientId. The exception represents a critical failure in the device's client lifecycle management system during the deregistration phase. ErrorDeregisterClientFailed is raised when the device attempts to remove a registered client from its active client registry and disable all transaction operations for that client, but encounters an internal error that prevents the state transition from completing successfully. This exception indicates that the device's client management subsystem has encountered a persistence failure, state inconsistency, or system-level error that prevents the client from being properly deregistered. The exception is raised after the deregistration request has been validated and the deregistration log entry has been created, but before the client's active status has been successfully removed from the internal registry.</description>
  <category>Client Management</category>
  <severity>High</severity>
  <javadoc>
    <summary>This class defines the exception ErrorDeregisterClientFailed that is thrown if the SE API function deregisterClient fails to disable the invocation of startTransaction, updateTransaction and finishTransaction for the specified clientId.</summary>
    <description>The deregistration operation of a client application from the device encountered a failure condition. This exception indicates that the deregisterClient function was unable to successfully disable the ability for the specified client to invoke transaction functions. This failure may occur due to internal state management issues, persistence failures, or system-level errors during the deregistration process.</description>
  </javadoc>
  <specification>
    <source>BSI TR-03151-1</source>
    <section>3.7.4.4</section>
    <requirement>SHALL be raised when the deregistration of the client fails. If the disabling of the function invocation using the clientId fails, the function SHALL raise the exception ErrorDeregisterClientFailed and exit the function.</requirement>
    <applicability>Client deregistration operations when disabling client access fails</applicability>
    <reference>deregisterClient – Exceptions (3.7.4.4)</reference>
  </specification>
  <thrownBy>
    <function>deregisterClient</function>
  </thrownBy>
  <triggerConditions>
    <condition>
      <scenario>Client registry update failure during deregistration</scenario>
      <description>The device accepts the deregistration request for a valid registered clientId, creates a deregistration log entry successfully, but encounters an error when attempting to update the internal client registry to remove the client from active status.</description>
      <trigger>Internal client registry persistence failure preventing removal of clientId from active list</trigger>
    </condition>
    <condition>
      <scenario>State management inconsistency in client subsystem</scenario>
      <description>The device's client management subsystem has entered an inconsistent state where client registry and client state tracking are out of synchronization. Deregistration fails because the subsystem cannot reliably update its state.</description>
      <trigger>Client management subsystem state inconsistency preventing status transition</trigger>
    </condition>
    <condition>
      <scenario>Open transaction blocking deregistration</scenario>
      <description>The client being deregistered has one or more open or incomplete transactions. The device prevents deregistration to avoid orphaned transactions, raising this exception to indicate that transactions must be closed before deregistration can proceed.</description>
      <trigger>Active transactions prevent client deregistration</trigger>
    </condition>
    <condition>
      <scenario>Device storage or persistence failure</scenario>
      <description>The device's storage system fails to persist the client state change (removal of client from active registry). This can occur due to storage errors, permission issues, or corruption in the client registry storage.</description>
      <trigger>Storage or persistence failure when updating client registry</trigger>
    </condition>
    <condition>
      <scenario>Client management subsystem malfunction</scenario>
      <description>The client management subsystem has encountered a runtime error, exception, or malfunction that prevents it from processing the deregistration operation. The error may originate from firmware issues or internal subsystem failures.</description>
      <trigger>Client management subsystem runtime error or malfunction</trigger>
    </condition>
  </triggerConditions>
  <recovery>
    <step>Verify client exists using getRegisteredClients</step>
    <step>Ensure no open transactions exist for this client before deregistration</step>
    <step>Retry deregistration after cleaning up client transactions</step>
    <step>Check device state and storage conditions</step>
    <step>Verify user has authorization to deregister clients</step>
  </recovery>
  <relatedExceptions>
    <exception>ErrorClientNotRegistered</exception>
    <exception>ErrorRegisterClientFailed</exception>
    <exception>ErrorClientAlreadyRegistered</exception>
    <exception>ErrorClientLimitReached</exception>
  </relatedExceptions>
  <executionSequence>
    <step number="1" name="Function Invocation">Function entry point is reached with clientId parameter specifying the client to be deregistered</step>
    <step number="2" name="Parameter Validation">The Secure Element validates that clientId is non-null and properly formatted for internal client registry lookups</step>
    <step number="3" name="Client Existence Check">The device verifies that the specified clientId is currently registered in the active client registry</step>
    <step number="4" name="Transaction Completion Check">The device checks whether any open or incomplete transactions are associated with the client. If found, execution branches to step 5b; if none found, execution continues to step 6</step>
    <step number="5a" name="No Blocking Transactions">No open transactions exist for the client, and deregistration may proceed</step>
    <step number="5b" name="Blocking Transactions Exist">Open transactions exist; depending on implementation, deregistration may be blocked or transactions may need to be force-closed</step>
    <step number="6" name="Deregistration Log Entry Creation">A deregistration event is created and stored in the device's audit trail and logging subsystem to record the deregistration attempt</step>
    <step number="7" name="Client Registry Update Attempt">The device attempts to remove the clientId from the active client registry and update all state data structures to reflect the client's inactive status</step>
    <step number="8a" name="Registry Update Success">If registry update completes successfully, execution continues to function completion (not taken in this exception case)</step>
    <step number="8b" name="Registry Update Failure">If the registry update fails due to persistence error, state inconsistency, or subsystem malfunction, execution branches to step 9</step>
    <step number="9" name="Exception Context Preparation">Exception context is prepared including clientId, deregistration log entry that was created, current client registry state, and error details from the client management subsystem</step>
    <step number="10" name="Exception Instance Creation">ErrorDeregisterClientFailed exception instance is created with appropriate error message indicating the client deregistration failure</step>
    <step number="11" name="Exception Propagation">Exception is raised and propagated up the call stack to the calling application, leaving the client in a potentially inconsistent state</step>
  </executionSequence>
  <postconditionality>
    <state name="Exception State">An ErrorDeregisterClientFailed exception has been created and raised, containing clientId, deregistration log information, and client management subsystem error details</state>
    <state name="Deregistration Log State">A deregistration event has been successfully recorded in the device's audit trail and logging subsystem. This log entry documents the deregistration attempt even though it failed to complete.</state>
    <state name="Client Registry State">The client remains in an inconsistent state. The deregistration log entry exists, but the client may still be present in the active registry or in a partially deregistered state. The client's transaction access may or may not be disabled.</state>
    <state name="Transaction Capability State">The ability to invoke startTransaction, updateTransaction, and finishTransaction with this clientId remains unchanged or is in an indeterminate state. Applications cannot rely on the client being disabled.</state>
    <state name="Device State">The device remains operational, but the client management subsystem has encountered an error condition. Subsequent client registration and deregistration operations may also fail or may succeed depending on whether the underlying issue is transient.</state>
    <state name="Function Exit">The function exits abnormally via exception propagation without completing the client deregistration operation</state>
  </postconditionality>
  <notes>
    <note>Indication: Deregistration of a client failed - client remains registered</note>
    <note>Topics: Client Management, Deregistration, Client Lifecycle, Registry Operations</note>
  </notes>
  <usage>
    <scenario name="Scenario 1: Client Cleanup with Blocking Transactions">
      <description>An application attempts to deregister a client at shutdown time, but the client has one or more open transactions that prevent deregistration. The application must close all transactions before deregistration can succeed.</description>
      <relatedFunctions>deregisterClient, finishTransaction, getCurrentNumberOfClients</relatedFunctions>
      <errorContext>Client lifecycle management where incomplete transactions block deregistration</errorContext>
    </scenario>
    <scenario name="Scenario 2: Client Registry Corruption During Deregistration">
      <description>A device has been operating normally, but after repeated deregistration operations, the client management subsystem enters a corrupted state. New deregistration attempts fail with this exception.</description>
      <relatedFunctions>deregisterClient, getDeviceHealth, initializeDevice</relatedFunctions>
      <errorContext>Progressive corruption of client management subsystem manifesting as deregistration failures</errorContext>
    </scenario>
    <scenario name="Scenario 3: Retry-Based Deregistration with State Verification">
      <description>An application receives this exception during deregistration and implements a recovery strategy: verify current client state, close any remaining transactions, and retry deregistration after subsystem stabilization.</description>
      <relatedFunctions>deregisterClient, getRegisteredClients, finishTransaction</relatedFunctions>
      <errorContext>Resilient client lifecycle management with state verification and retry logic</errorContext>
    </scenario>
    <scenario name="Scenario 4: Device-Level Client Cleanup">
      <description>Multiple clients fail to deregister with this exception. The application recognizes that the client management subsystem is fundamentally broken and initiates device reinitialization to restore the system to a clean state.</description>
      <relatedFunctions>deregisterClient, initializeDevice, getDeviceHealth</relatedFunctions>
      <errorContext>System-level recovery where device reinitialization is required to fix corrupted client management</errorContext>
    </scenario>
  </usage>
  <implementationContext>
    <note>Raised by deregisterClient when client removal from registry fails</note>
    <note>Client lifecycle management includes deregistration of inactive clients</note>
    <note>Device removes client from active registry and associated resources</note>
    <note>Deregistration failure prevents client cleanup and resource release</note>
  </implementationContext>
</exception>
