<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8' standalone='yes'?>
<exception xmlns="http://bsi.bund.de/TR03151" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" id="ErrorDeviceInitializationFailed" xsi:schemaLocation="http://bsi.bund.de/TR03151 ../../schema/exceptions.xsd">
  <name>ErrorDeviceInitializationFailed</name>
  <description>This exception is thrown if any necessary action to initialize the device fails during execution of the initialize function. The exception represents a critical failure in the device's startup sequence that prevents the device from entering an operational state. ErrorDeviceInitializationFailed is raised when the device attempts to perform one or more essential initialization actions (such as Secure Element activation, internal state setup, client registry creation, logging system initialization, or cryptographic key loading), but encounters a hardware error, firmware issue, state management failure, or system-level error that prevents successful completion. This exception indicates that the device initialization process has partially failed at some critical checkpoint, leaving the device in an uninitialized and unusable state. The exception is raised after the device has attempted initialization but before all necessary initialization steps have been completed and verified.</description>
  <category>Initialization</category>
  <subcategory>Initialization Process</subcategory>
  <severity>Critical</severity>
  <javadoc>
    <summary>This class defines the exception ErrorDeviceInitializationFailed that is thrown if any necessary action to initialize the device fails.</summary>
    <description>The device initialization process encountered a failure condition during execution of the initialize function. This exception indicates that one or more necessary actions required to properly initialize the device could not be completed successfully. This failure may occur due to hardware issues, state management problems, internal system errors, or failures in device component initialization.</description>
  </javadoc>
  <specification>
    <source>BSI TR-03151-1</source>
    <section>3.3.1.5</section>
    <requirement>SHALL be raised if any necessary action to initialize the device fails. The function SHALL perform all necessary actions to initialize the device. If the initialization fails, the function SHALL raise the exception ErrorDeviceInitializationFailed and exit the function.</requirement>
    <applicability>Device initialization operations when initialization process fails</applicability>
    <reference>initialize – Exceptions (3.3.1.4)</reference>
  </specification>
  <thrownBy>
    <function>initialize</function>
  </thrownBy>
  <triggerConditions>
    <condition>
      <scenario>Secure Element activation or communication failure</scenario>
      <description>The device attempts to activate or establish communication with the Secure Element during initialization, but encounters a hardware error, firmware issue, or communication failure that prevents successful activation or prevents the Secure Element from becoming accessible.</description>
      <trigger>Secure Element hardware failure, firmware error, or communication failure during initialization</trigger>
    </condition>
    <condition>
      <scenario>Internal device state management initialization failure</scenario>
      <description>The device initializes internal state management structures (client registry, transaction tracking, logging configuration, resource management), but encounters errors in setting up these critical subsystems. Memory allocation failures, storage access issues, or state inconsistencies prevent state initialization.</description>
      <trigger>Internal state management subsystem initialization failure</trigger>
    </condition>
    <condition>
      <scenario>Device component hardware failure</scenario>
      <description>One or more hardware components required for device operation are detected to be non-functional during initialization diagnostics. This may include storage media, cryptographic processors, communication interfaces, or sensor components.</description>
      <trigger>Hardware component failure detected during initialization self-test</trigger>
    </condition>
    <condition>
      <scenario>Cryptographic key or certificate initialization failure</scenario>
      <description>The device must load, verify, or generate cryptographic keys and certificates during initialization. Failure to load keys from storage, verification failures, or key generation errors prevent successful initialization.</description>
      <trigger>Cryptographic key or certificate initialization failure</trigger>
    </condition>
    <condition>
      <scenario>Device firmware or boot sequence failure</scenario>
      <description>The device firmware or boot sequence encounters errors that prevent successful completion. Firmware corruption, boot block damage, or firmware update incomplete scenarios prevent the device from transitioning to an operational state.</description>
      <trigger>Firmware or boot sequence failure during device initialization</trigger>
    </condition>
  </triggerConditions>
  <recovery>
    <step>Check device self-test status using selfTest</step>
    <step>Verify Secure Element is functional and connected</step>
    <step>Confirm device storage is accessible and not full</step>
    <step>Retry initialization after confirming prerequisites</step>
    <step>Contact device vendor if initialization persistently fails</step>
  </recovery>
  <relatedExceptions>
    <exception>ErrorDeviceIsInitialized</exception>
    <exception>ErrorFunctionFailed</exception>
    <exception>ErrorSigningEventDataFailed</exception>
    <exception>ErrorSecureElementDisabled</exception>
  </relatedExceptions>
  <executionSequence>
    <step number="1" name="Function Invocation">Function entry point is reached for initialize with no parameters required</step>
    <step number="2" name="Current State Check">The device checks its current state to verify it is not already initialized. If already initialized, ErrorDeviceIsInitialized is raised instead (not taken in this exception case)</step>
    <step number="3" name="Secure Element Communication Initialization">The device establishes communication with the Secure Element hardware and verifies that it is responsive and accessible</step>
    <step number="4" name="Internal State Structure Creation">The device creates and initializes internal state management structures including client registry, transaction tracking, and resource management tables</step>
    <step number="5" name="Storage System Verification">The device verifies that all storage media are accessible, functional, and properly formatted for logging and data persistence</step>
    <step number="6" name="Cryptographic Key Loading">The device loads cryptographic keys and certificates from protected storage and verifies their validity and integrity</step>
    <step number="7" name="Logging System Initialization">The device initializes the logging subsystem, creates initial log entries, and verifies logging capability</step>
    <step number="8" name="Device Self-Test Execution">The device performs self-test and diagnostic checks on critical hardware components to verify functional status</step>
    <step number="9" name="Initialization Completion Verification">The device verifies that all initialization steps have completed successfully and the device is ready for operation</step>
    <step number="10a" name="Initialization Success">If all initialization steps complete successfully, the device enters an initialized state and the function returns normally (not taken in this exception case)</step>
    <step number="10b" name="Initialization Failure">If any critical initialization step fails, execution branches to exception handling at step 11</step>
    <step number="11" name="Exception Context Preparation">Exception context is prepared including the specific initialization step that failed, error details from the failed component, and device state information</step>
    <step number="12" name="Exception Instance Creation">ErrorDeviceInitializationFailed exception instance is created with appropriate error message indicating which initialization action failed</step>
    <step number="13" name="Exception Propagation">Exception is raised and propagated up the call stack, leaving the device in an uninitialized and non-operational state</step>
  </executionSequence>
  <postconditionality>
    <state name="Exception State">An ErrorDeviceInitializationFailed exception has been created and raised, containing information about the failed initialization step and component error details</state>
    <state name="Device Operational State">The device remains in an uninitialized state and is not operational for SE API functions. No SE API functions other than initialize can be called on this device.</state>
    <state name="Device Internal State">The device may have partially initialized some internal structures (Secure Element communication, state tables, storage verification), but the overall device state is inconsistent and unsuitable for operation.</state>
    <state name="Secure Element State">The Secure Element may be accessible or initialized, depending on where the initialization process failed. The Secure Element may be in a transient state that requires reset.</state>
    <state name="Data Integrity State">Existing data in device storage may be inaccessible or unverified due to incomplete initialization. The device cannot be relied upon to provide data consistency.</state>
    <state name="Function Exit">The function exits abnormally via exception propagation without completing device initialization</state>
  </postconditionality>
  <notes>
    <note>Indication: Device initialization failed - device could not be properly set up</note>
    <note>Topics: Device Initialization, Setup Operations, Device State, System Configuration</note>
  </notes>
  <usage>
    <scenario name="Scenario 1: Hardware Failure During First Initialization">
      <description>A newly deployed device fails during the initial initialization attempt due to a hardware component being non-functional. The device requires hardware diagnosis and repair.</description>
      <relatedFunctions>initialize, getComponentVersions, getDeviceHealth</relatedFunctions>
      <errorContext>Device deployment failure where hardware issue prevents initialization</errorContext>
    </scenario>
    <scenario name="Scenario 2: Firmware Corruption After Update">
      <description>A device was previously operational, but after a firmware update, initialization fails due to firmware corruption or incomplete update. Device requires firmware recovery or rollback.</description>
      <relatedFunctions>initialize, updateDevice, getComponentVersions</relatedFunctions>
      <errorContext>Firmware update failure leading to initialization failure</errorContext>
    </scenario>
    <scenario name="Scenario 3: Transient Initialization Failure with Retry Recovery">
      <description>An application encounters this exception during initialization but implements a retry strategy with increasing backoff delays. After 2-3 retries with delays, the device successfully initializes, indicating a transient hardware or timing issue.</description>
      <relatedFunctions>initialize, getDeviceHealth</relatedFunctions>
      <errorContext>Transient failure recovery through retry with backoff</errorContext>
    </scenario>
    <scenario name="Scenario 4: Persistent Failure Triggering Device Replacement">
      <description>Repeated initialization attempts fail consistently. After diagnostic checks confirm hardware damage or firmware corruption that cannot be repaired, the device is marked for replacement and failover to a backup device is activated.</description>
      <relatedFunctions>initialize, getDeviceHealth, getComponentVersions</relatedFunctions>
      <errorContext>Persistent device failure requiring replacement and failover</errorContext>
    </scenario>
  </usage>
  <implementationContext>
    <note>Raised by initialize when device setup and initialization fails</note>
    <note>Initialization function sets up device state, storage, and cryptographic components</note>
    <note>Device performs self-tests and validates internal components during initialization</note>
    <note>Initialization failure prevents device from reaching ready state</note>
  </implementationContext>
</exception>

