<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<function xmlns="http://bsi.bund.de/TR03151" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" id="getCurrentTransactionCounter" xsi:schemaLocation="http://bsi.bund.de/TR03151 ../../schema/functions.xsd">
  <name>getCurrentTransactionCounter</name>
  <category>Client- und Transaktionsverwaltung</category>
  <description>The function getOpenTransactions can be used to obtain the transaction numbers of open transactions that are currently managed by the device.</description>
  <detailedSteps>
    <step>
      <number>1</number>
      <originalText>If the referencing guideline limits the access to the functionality solely to authenticated users, the function SHALL check if the user that has invoked the function has the status authenticated. If the status is not authenticated, the function SHALL raise the exception ErrorUserNotAuthenticated and exit the function.</originalText>
      <germanText>Prüft, ob Nutzer authentifiziert. Falls nicht: Exception ErrorUserNotAuthenticated, Ende.</germanText>
      <pseudocode>WENN Benutzer NICHT authentifiziert DANN
  WERFE ErrorUserNotAuthenticated
  BEENDE_FUNKTION
ENDE</pseudocode>
      <errorCase>
        <exception>ErrorUserNotAuthenticated</exception>
        <trigger>Der Benutzer ist nicht authentifiziert</trigger>
        <action>Funktion beenden</action>
      </errorCase>
    </step>
    <step>
      <number>2</number>
      <originalText>If the referencing guideline limits the access to the functionality to certain roles, the function SHALL check in the corresponding role if the (unauthenticated) user is authorized to execute the function. If the user is not authorized, the function SHALL raise the exception ErrorUserNotAuthorized and exit the function.</originalText>
      <germanText>Prüft, ob Nutzer berechtigt. Falls nicht: Exception ErrorUserNotAuthorized, Ende.</germanText>
      <pseudocode>WENN Benutzer NICHT autorisiert DANN
  WERFE ErrorUserNotAuthorized
  BEENDE_FUNKTION
ENDE</pseudocode>
      <errorCase>
        <exception>ErrorUserNotAuthorized</exception>
        <trigger>Der Benutzer ist nicht berechtigt</trigger>
        <action>Funktion beenden</action>
      </errorCase>
    </step>
    <step>
      <number>3</number>
      <originalText>The function SHALL determine the transaction number of the last opened transaction. If the determination of the current transaction number fails, the function SHALL raise the exception ErrorGetCurrentTransactionCounterFailed and exit the function.</originalText>
      <germanText>Ermittelt letzte Transaktionsnummer. Bei Fehler: Exception ErrorGetCurrentTransactionCounterFailed, Ende.</germanText>
      <pseudocode>VERSUCHE
  ERMITTLE Transaktionsnummer der letzten geöffneten Transaktion
BEI_FEHLER
  WERFE ErrorGetCurrentTransactionCounterFailed
  BEENDE_FUNKTION
ENDE</pseudocode>
      <errorCase>
        <exception>ErrorGetCurrentTransactionCounterFailed</exception>
        <trigger>Die Ermittlung der Transaktionsnummer schlägt fehl</trigger>
        <action>Funktion beenden</action>
      </errorCase>
    </step>
    <step>
      <number>4</number>
      <originalText>If the determination of the current transaction number has been successful, the function SHALL return the current transaction number (as an output parameter) by transactionNumber. The function SHALL return without raising an exception to indicate that the execution of the function has been successful.</originalText>
      <germanText>Gibt Transaktionsnummer zurück. Bei Erfolg keine Exception.</germanText>
      <pseudocode>GEBE aktuelle Transaktionsnummer zurück (transactionNumber Parameter)
RETURN ohne Exception</pseudocode>
      <successCase>
        <condition>Die Ermittlung der aktuellen Transaktionsnummer war erfolgreich</condition>
        <action>Gibt Transaktionsnummer zurück und kehrt ohne Exception zurück</action>
      </successCase>
    </step>
  </detailedSteps>
  <parameters />
  <returnValue>
    <type>long</type>
    <description>the current value of the transaction counter.</description>
  </returnValue>
  <exceptions>
    <exception>ErrorDeviceNotInitialized</exception>
    <exception>ErrorFunctionFailed</exception>
    <exception>ErrorFunctionNotSupported</exception>
    <exception>ErrorGetCurrentTransactionCounterFailed</exception>
    <exception>ErrorParameterSyntax</exception>
    <exception>ErrorSecureElementDisabled</exception>
    <exception>ErrorUserNotAuthenticated</exception>
    <exception>ErrorUserNotAuthorized</exception>
  </exceptions>
</function>
