<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<function id="getDeviceHealth" xmlns="http://bsi.bund.de/TR03151" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://bsi.bund.de/TR03151 ../../schema/functions.xsd">
  <name>getDeviceHealth</name>
  <category>Gerätewartung</category>
  <description>The function getDeviceHealth can be used to determine the health of the device or the components that form the device.</description>
  <detailedSteps>
    <step>
      <number>1</number>
      <originalText>If the referencing guideline limits the access to the functionality solely to authenticated users, the function SHALL check if the user that has invoked the function has the status authenticated. If the status is not authenticated, the function SHALL raise the exception ErrorUserNotAuthenticated and exit the function.</originalText>
      <germanText>Prüft, ob Nutzer authentifiziert. Falls nicht: Exception ErrorUserNotAuthenticated, Ende.</germanText>
      <pseudocode>WENN Benutzer NICHT authentifiziert DANN
  WERFE ErrorUserNotAuthenticated
  BEENDE_FUNKTION
ENDE</pseudocode>
      <errorCase>
        <exception>ErrorUserNotAuthenticated</exception>
        <trigger>Der Benutzer ist nicht authentifiziert</trigger>
        <action>Funktion beenden</action>
      </errorCase>
    </step>
    <step>
      <number>2</number>
      <originalText>If the referencing guideline limits the access to the functionality to certain roles, the function SHALL check in the corresponding role if the (unauthenticated) user is authorized to execute the function. If the user is not authorized, the function SHALL raise the exception ErrorUserNotAuthorized and exit the function.</originalText>
      <germanText>Prüft, ob Nutzer berechtigt. Falls nicht: Exception ErrorUserNotAuthorized, Ende.</germanText>
      <pseudocode>WENN Benutzer NICHT autorisiert DANN
  WERFE ErrorUserNotAuthorized
  BEENDE_FUNKTION
ENDE</pseudocode>
      <errorCase>
        <exception>ErrorUserNotAuthorized</exception>
        <trigger>Der Benutzer ist nicht berechtigt</trigger>
        <action>Funktion beenden</action>
      </errorCase>
    </step>
    <step>
      <number>3</number>
      <originalText>The function SHALL determine the health of the device or the components that form the device. If the determination of the health information fails, the function SHALL raise the exception ErrorGetDeviceHealthFailed and exit the function.</originalText>
      <germanText>Ermittelt Gerätezustand. Bei Fehler: Exception ErrorGetDeviceHealthFailed, Ende.</germanText>
      <pseudocode>VERSUCHE
  ERMITTLE Gerätezustand
BEI_FEHLER
  WERFE ErrorGetDeviceHealthFailed
  BEENDE_FUNKTION
ENDE</pseudocode>
      <errorCase>
        <exception>ErrorGetDeviceHealthFailed</exception>
        <trigger>Die Ermittlung der Integritätsinformationen schlägt fehl</trigger>
        <action>Funktion beenden</action>
      </errorCase>
    </step>
    <step>
      <number>4</number>
      <originalText>If the determination of the health information has been successful, the function SHALL return the information by usage of the output parameter healthInformationSet. Additionally, the function SHALL return without raising an exception to indicate that the execution of the function has been successful.</originalText>
      <germanText>Gibt Gerätezustand zurück. Bei Erfolg keine Exception.</germanText>
      <pseudocode>GEBE Gerätezustandsinformationen zurück (healthInformationSet Parameter)
RETURN ohne Exception</pseudocode>
      <successCase>
        <condition>Die Ermittlung der Gerätezustandsinformationen war erfolgreich</condition>
        <action>Gibt Zustandsinformationen zurück und kehrt ohne Exception zurück</action>
      </successCase>
    </step>
  </detailedSteps>
  <parameters />
  <returnValue>
    <type>byte[]</type>
    <description>the health state of the device.</description>
  </returnValue>
  <exceptions>
    <exception>ErrorDeviceNotInitialized</exception>
    <exception>ErrorFunctionFailed</exception>
    <exception>ErrorFunctionNotSupported</exception>
    <exception>ErrorGetDeviceHealthFailed</exception>
    <exception>ErrorParameterSyntax</exception>
    <exception>ErrorStorageMediumDisconnected</exception>
    <exception>ErrorUserNotAuthenticated</exception>
    <exception>ErrorUserNotAuthorized</exception>
  </exceptions>
</function>
