<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<function id="getEndOfUsageDate" xmlns="http://bsi.bund.de/TR03151" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://bsi.bund.de/TR03151 ../../schema/functions.xsd">
  <name>getEndOfUsageDate</name>
  <category>Gerätewartung</category>
  <description>Electrical devices may be subject to aging or wear and tear. Sometimes this process is observable or predictable. The API function getDeviceHealth can be used to get information about the actual health of the device or the components within.</description>
  <detailedSteps>
    <step>
      <number>1</number>
      <originalText>If the referencing guideline limits the access to the functionality solely to authenticated users, the function SHALL check if the user that has invoked the function has the status authenticated. If the status is not authenticated, the function SHALL raise the exception ErrorUserNotAuthenticated and exit the function.</originalText>
      <germanText>Prüft, ob Nutzer authentifiziert. Falls nicht: Exception ErrorUserNotAuthenticated, Ende.</germanText>
      <pseudocode>WENN Benutzer NICHT authentifiziert DANN
  WERFE ErrorUserNotAuthenticated
  BEENDE_FUNKTION
ENDE</pseudocode>
      <errorCase>
        <exception>ErrorUserNotAuthenticated</exception>
        <trigger>Der Benutzer ist nicht authentifiziert</trigger>
        <action>Funktion beenden</action>
      </errorCase>
    </step>
    <step>
      <number>2</number>
      <originalText>If the referencing guideline limits the access to the functionality to certain roles, the function SHALL check in the corresponding role if the (unauthenticated) user is authorized to execute the function. If the user is not authorized, the function SHALL raise the exception ErrorUserNotAuthorized and exit the function.</originalText>
      <germanText>Prüft, ob Nutzer berechtigt. Falls nicht: Exception ErrorUserNotAuthorized, Ende.</germanText>
      <pseudocode>WENN Benutzer NICHT autorisiert DANN
  WERFE ErrorUserNotAuthorized
  BEENDE_FUNKTION
ENDE</pseudocode>
      <errorCase>
        <exception>ErrorUserNotAuthorized</exception>
        <trigger>Der Benutzer ist nicht berechtigt</trigger>
        <action>Funktion beenden</action>
      </errorCase>
    </step>
    <step>
      <number>3</number>
      <originalText>The function SHALL determine the earliest date after which the input functions can no longer be used. Possible invocations of the functions disableSecureElement and lockTransactionLogging SHALL NOT be taken into account. If the determination of this date fails, the function SHALL raise the exception ErrorGetEndOfUsageDateFailed and exit the function.</originalText>
      <germanText>Ermittelt Enddatum der Nutzbarkeit. Bei Fehler: Exception ErrorGetEndOfUsageDateFailed, Ende.</germanText>
      <pseudocode>VERSUCHE
  ERMITTLE frühestes Enddatum der Nutzbarkeit
BEI_FEHLER
  WERFE ErrorGetEndOfUsageDateFailed
  BEENDE_FUNKTION
ENDE</pseudocode>
      <errorCase>
        <exception>ErrorGetEndOfUsageDateFailed</exception>
        <trigger>Die Ermittlung des Datums schlägt fehl</trigger>
        <action>Funktion beenden</action>
      </errorCase>
    </step>
    <step>
      <number>4</number>
      <originalText>If the determination of the earliest date after which the input functions can no longer be used has been successful, the function SHALL return this date by usage of the output parameter endOfUsageDate. Additionally, the function SHALL return without raising an exception to indicate that the execution of the function has been successful.</originalText>
      <germanText>Gibt Enddatum zurück. Bei Erfolg keine Exception.</germanText>
      <pseudocode>GEBE Enddatum zurück (endOfUsageDate Parameter)
RETURN ohne Exception</pseudocode>
      <successCase>
        <condition>Die Ermittlung des Enddatums war erfolgreich</condition>
        <action>Gibt das Enddatum zurück und kehrt ohne Exception zurück</action>
      </successCase>
    </step>
  </detailedSteps>
  <parameters />
  <returnValue>
    <type>ZonedDateTime</type>
    <description>the end of usage date of the device.</description>
  </returnValue>
  <exceptions>
    <exception>ErrorDeviceNotInitialized</exception>
    <exception>ErrorFunctionFailed</exception>
    <exception>ErrorFunctionNotSupported</exception>
    <exception>ErrorGetEndOfUsageDateFailed</exception>
    <exception>ErrorParameterSyntax</exception>
    <exception>ErrorSecureElementDisabled</exception>
    <exception>ErrorUserNotAuthenticated</exception>
    <exception>ErrorUserNotAuthorized</exception>
  </exceptions>
</function>
