<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<function id="getOpenTransactions" xmlns="http://bsi.bund.de/TR03151" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://bsi.bund.de/TR03151 ../../schema/functions.xsd">
  <name>getOpenTransactions</name>
  <category>Client- und Transaktionsverwaltung</category>
  <description>The function getOpenTransactions can be used to obtain the transaction numbers of open transactions for a specific client application.</description>
  <detailedSteps>
    <step>
      <number>1</number>
      <originalText>If the referencing guideline limits the access to the functionality solely to authenticated users, the function SHALL check if the user that has invoked the function has the status authenticated. If the status is not authenticated, the function SHALL raise the exception ErrorUserNotAuthenticated and exit the function.</originalText>
      <germanText>Falls die Richtlinie den Zugriff auf authentifizierte Benutzer beschränkt: Prüfe, ob der aufrufende Benutzer authentifiziert ist. Falls nicht: Werfe ErrorUserNotAuthenticated und beende Funktion.</germanText>
      <pseudocode>WENN Benutzer NICHT authentifiziert DANN
  WERFE ErrorUserNotAuthenticated
  BEENDE_FUNKTION
ENDE</pseudocode>
      <errorCase>
        <exception>ErrorUserNotAuthenticated</exception>
        <trigger>Der Benutzer ist nicht authentifiziert</trigger>
        <action>Funktion beenden</action>
      </errorCase>
    </step>
    <step>
      <number>2</number>
      <originalText>If the referencing guideline limits the access to the functionality to certain roles, the function SHALL check in the corresponding role if the (unauthenticated) user is authorized to execute the function. If the user is not authorized, the function SHALL raise the exception ErrorUserNotAuthorized and exit the function.</originalText>
      <germanText>Falls die Richtlinie den Zugriff auf bestimmte Rollen beschränkt: Prüfe in der entsprechenden Rolle, ob der (unauthentifizierte) Benutzer berechtigt ist, die Funktion auszuführen. Falls nicht: Werfe ErrorUserNotAuthorized und beende Funktion.</germanText>
      <pseudocode>WENN Benutzer NICHT autorisiert DANN
  WERFE ErrorUserNotAuthorized
  BEENDE_FUNKTION
ENDE</pseudocode>
      <errorCase>
        <exception>ErrorUserNotAuthorized</exception>
        <trigger>Der Benutzer ist nicht berechtigt</trigger>
        <action>Funktion beenden</action>
      </errorCase>
    </step>
    <step>
      <number>3</number>
      <originalText>The function SHALL determine all transactions that are currently open. If the determination of this fails, the function SHALL raise the exception ErrorGetOpenTransactionsFailed and exit the function.</originalText>
      <germanText>Funktion ermittelt alle derzeit offenen Transaktionen. Bei Fehler: ErrorGetOpenTransactionsFailed, Ende.</germanText>
      <pseudocode>VERSUCHE
  HOLE offene Transaktionen vom SE
BEI_FEHLER
  WERFE ErrorGetOpenTransactionsFailed
  BEENDE_FUNKTION
ENDE</pseudocode>
      <errorCase>
        <exception>ErrorGetOpenTransactionsFailed</exception>
        <trigger>Die Ermittlung schlägt fehl</trigger>
        <action>Funktion beenden</action>
      </errorCase>
    </step>
    <step>
      <number>4</number>
      <originalText>If the determination of the currently opened transactions is successful, the function SHALL return information on all currently opened transactions by usage of the output parameter openTransactions. Additionally, the function SHALL return without raising an exception to indicate that the execution of the function has been successful.</originalText>
      <germanText>Bei Erfolg der Ermittlung: Gibt alle offenen Transaktionen via Parameter openTransactions zurück. Keine Exception.</germanText>
      <pseudocode>GEBE offene Transaktionen zurück (openTransactions Parameter)
RETURN ohne Exception</pseudocode>
      <successCase>
        <condition>Ausführung war erfolgreich</condition>
        <action>Funktion kehrt ohne Exception zurück</action>
      </successCase>
    </step>
  </detailedSteps>
  <parameters />
  <returnValue>
    <type>byte[]</type>
    <description>list of currently open transactions.</description>
  </returnValue>
  <exceptions>
    <exception>ErrorDeviceNotInitialized</exception>
    <exception>ErrorFunctionFailed</exception>
    <exception>ErrorFunctionNotSupported</exception>
    <exception>ErrorGetOpenTransactionsFailed</exception>
    <exception>ErrorParameterSyntax</exception>
    <exception>ErrorSecureElementDisabled</exception>
    <exception>ErrorStorageMediumDisconnected</exception>
    <exception>ErrorUserNotAuthenticated</exception>
    <exception>ErrorUserNotAuthorized</exception>
  </exceptions>
</function>
