<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<function id="restoreLogsFromBackup" xmlns="http://bsi.bund.de/TR03151" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://bsi.bund.de/TR03151 ../../schema/functions.xsd">
  <name>restoreLogsFromBackup</name>
  <category>Logging</category>
  <description>Exports the serial number(s) of the SE API. A serial number is a hash value of a public key that belongs to a key pair, whose private key is used to create signature values of log messages.</description>
  <detailedSteps>
    <step>
      <number>1</number>
      <originalText>If the referencing guideline limits the access to the functionality solely to authenticated users, the function SHALL check if the user that has invoked the function has the status authenticated. If the status is not authenticated, the function SHALL raise the exception ErrorUserNotAuthenticated and exit the function.</originalText>
      <germanText>Falls die Richtlinie den Zugriff auf authentifizierte Benutzer beschränkt: Prüfe, ob der aufrufende Benutzer authentifiziert ist. Falls nicht: Werfe ErrorUserNotAuthenticated und beende Funktion.</germanText>
      <pseudocode>WENN Benutzer NICHT authentifiziert DANN
  WERFE ErrorUserNotAuthenticated
  BEENDE_FUNKTION
ENDE</pseudocode>
      <errorCase>
        <exception>ErrorUserNotAuthenticated</exception>
        <trigger>Der Benutzer ist nicht authentifiziert</trigger>
        <action>Funktion beenden</action>
      </errorCase>
    </step>
    <step>
      <number>2</number>
      <originalText>If the referencing guideline limits the access to the functionality to certain roles, the function SHALL check in the corresponding role if the (unauthenticated) user is authorized to execute the function. If the user is not authorized, the function SHALL raise the exception ErrorUserNotAuthorized and exit the function.</originalText>
      <germanText>Falls die Richtlinie den Zugriff auf bestimmte Rollen beschränkt: Prüfe in der entsprechenden Rolle, ob der (unauthentifizierte) Benutzer berechtigt ist, die Funktion auszuführen. Falls nicht: Werfe ErrorUserNotAuthorized und beende Funktion.</germanText>
      <pseudocode>WENN Benutzer NICHT autorisiert DANN
  WERFE ErrorUserNotAuthorized
  BEENDE_FUNKTION
ENDE</pseudocode>
      <errorCase>
        <exception>ErrorUserNotAuthorized</exception>
        <trigger>Der Benutzer ist nicht berechtigt</trigger>
        <action>Funktion beenden</action>
      </errorCase>
    </step>
    <step>
      <number>3</number>
      <originalText>The function SHALL process the passed data and store the data of the passed log messages in the storage. If the passed data contains log messages not created by the device, the function SHALL reject the import of the logs, raise the exception ErrorRestoreFailed, and exit the function. In case file names of log files are stored by the device prior to an export and an imported log message has a file name that already exists in the storage, a counter SHALL be appended to the file name of the imported log message (see chapter 2.5.5). If the storing of the passed log message data fails, the function SHALL raise the exception ErrorRestoreFailed and exit the function.</originalText>
      <germanText>Verarbeite die übergebenen Daten und speichere die Log-Nachrichten. Bei Fehler oder ungültigen Log-Nachrichten: ErrorRestoreFailed, Ende.</germanText>
      <pseudocode>VERSUCHE
  SPEICHERE Log-Nachrichtendaten
BEI_FEHLER
  WERFE ErrorRestoreFailed
  BEENDE_FUNKTION
ENDE</pseudocode>
      <errorCase>
        <exception>ErrorRestoreFailed</exception>
        <trigger>Das Speichern der Log-Nachrichtendaten schlägt fehl</trigger>
        <action>Funktion beenden</action>
      </errorCase>
    </step>
    <step>
      <number>4</number>
      <originalText>If no certificate of the same file name already exists, the function SHALL store the passed certificates. If a certificate has not been stored successfully, the function SHALL raise the exception ErrorRestoreFailed and exit the function.</originalText>
      <germanText>Falls kein Zertifikat mit gleichem Dateinamen vorhanden ist: Speichere die Zertifikate. Bei Fehler: ErrorRestoreFailed, Ende.</germanText>
      <pseudocode>VERSUCHE
  SPEICHERE Zertifikate
BEI_FEHLER
  WERFE ErrorRestoreFailed
  BEENDE_FUNKTION
ENDE</pseudocode>
      <errorCase>
        <exception>ErrorRestoreFailed</exception>
        <trigger>Ein Zertifikat wurde nicht erfolgreich gespeichert</trigger>
        <action>Funktion beenden</action>
      </errorCase>
    </step>
    <step>
      <number>5</number>
      <originalText>If the restoring has been successful, the function SHALL return without raising an exception to indicate that the execution of the function has been successful.</originalText>
      <germanText>Bei erfolgreicher Wiederherstellung: Gebe ohne Exception zurück.</germanText>
      <pseudocode>RETURN ohne Exception
BEENDE_ERFOLGREICH</pseudocode>
      <successCase>
        <condition>Wiederherstellung erfolgreich</condition>
        <action>Gibt Erfolg ohne Exception zurück</action>
      </successCase>
    </step>
  </detailedSteps>
  <parameters>
    <parameter>
      <name>restoreData</name>
      <type>InputStream</type>
      <description>the backup data to be restored.</description>
      <direction>INPUT</direction>
      <required>true</required>
    </parameter>
  </parameters>
  <returnValue>
    <type>void</type>
    <description>This function does not return a value.</description>
  </returnValue>
  <exceptions>
    <exception>ErrorDeviceNotInitialized</exception>
    <exception>ErrorFunctionFailed</exception>
    <exception>ErrorFunctionNotSupported</exception>
    <exception>ErrorParameterSyntax</exception>
    <exception>ErrorParameterTooLong</exception>
    <exception>ErrorRestoreFailed</exception>
    <exception>ErrorStorageMediumDisconnected</exception>
    <exception>ErrorStorageMemoryFull</exception>
    <exception>ErrorUserNotAuthenticated</exception>
    <exception>ErrorUserNotAuthorized</exception>
  </exceptions>
</function>
